{
  "id": "art_pyq",
  "displayName": " Art & Culture",
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "The well-known painting 'Bani Thani' belongs to the _____________.    [UPSC 2018  ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) Bundi school "        , 
        " (b) Jaipur school  "            ,   
        " (c) Kangra school "                  , 
        "  (d) Kishangarh school "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": " Which reference to the religious practices in India, the 'Sthanakvasi' sect belongs to    [UPSC 2018  ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) Buddhism "        , 
        " (b) Jainism "            ,   
        "(c) Vaishnavism  "                  , 
        " (d) Shaivism  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": "With reference to the cultural history of India, consider the following statements: \n 1. White marble was used in making Buland Darwaza and Khankah at Fatehpur Sikri. \n 2. Red sandstone and marble were used in making Bara Imambara and Rumi Darwaza at Lucknow. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?  [UPSC 2018  ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) 1 only  "        , 
        " (b) 2 only  "            ,   
        " (c) Both 1 and 2  "                  , 
        " (d) Neither 1 nor 2  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 0
    },{
      "question": "Which reference to Indian history, who among the following is a future Buddha, yet to come to save the world?      [UPSC 2018  ]",
      "choices": [
        "(a) Avalokiteshvara  "        , 
        " (b) Lokesvara "            ,   
        " (c) Maityera "                  , 
        " (d) Padmapani "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 2
    },{
      "question": "With reference to the cultural history of India, which one of the following is the correct description of the term paramitas?   [UPSC 2020 ]",
      "choices": [
        "(a) The earliest Dharmashastra texts written in aphoristic (sutra) style  "        , 
        "  (b) Philosophical schools that did not accept the authority of Vedas "            ,   
        " (c) Perfections whose attainment led to the Bodhisattva path  "                  , 
        " (d) Powerful merchant guilds of early Medieval South India  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 2
    },{
      "question": "With reference to the religious history of India, consider the following statements: \n 1. Sthaviravadins belong to Mahayana Buddhism. \n 2. Lokottaravadin sect was an offshoot of Mahasanghika sect of Buddhism. \n 3. The deification of Buddha by Mahasanghikas fostered the Mahayana Buddhism. \n Which of the statements given above is/are Correct?  [UPSC 2020 ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) 1 and 2 only  "        , 
        "(b) 2 and 3 only  "            ,   
        "  (c) 3 only  "                  , 
        " (d) 1, 2 and 3  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": "With reference to India, the terms 'Halbi, Ho and Kui' pertain to     [UPSC 2021  ]",
      "choices": [
        "(a) dance forms of Northwest India  "        , 
        " (b) musical instruments "            ,   
        " (c) pre-historic cave paintings "                  , 
        " (d) tribal languages "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 3
    },{
      "question": "With reference to Indian history, consider the following texts: \n 1. Nettipakarana \n 2. Parishishtaparvan \n 3. Avadanashataka \n 4. Trishashtilakshana Mahapurana \n Which of the above are Jaina texts?      [UPSC 2022 ]",
      "choices": [
        "(a) 1, 2 and 3  "        , 
        "(b) 2 and 4 only  "            ,   
        " (c) 1, 3 and 4 "                  , 
        "(d) 2, 3 and 4  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": "With reference to Indian history, consider the following pairs: Historical person Known as \n1. Aryadeva - Jaina scholar \n2. Dignaga - Buddhist scholar \n3. Nathamuni - Vaishnava scholar \nHow many pairs given above are correctly matched?      [UPSC 2022  ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) None of the pairs "        , 
        "(b) Only one pair  "            ,   
        " (c) Only two pairs "                  , 
        "(d) All three pairs  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 2
    },{
      "question": "'Yogavasistha' was translated into Persian by Nizamuddin Panipati during the reign of _______________.      [UPSC 2022  ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) Akbar "        , 
        " (b) Humayun "            ,   
        " (c) Shahjahan "                  , 
        "  (d) Aurangzeb"         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": " Which one of the following statements about Sangam literature in ancient South India is correct?     [UPSC 2022 ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) Sangam poems are devoid of any reference to material culture. "        , 
        " (b) The social classification of Varna was known to Sangam poets. "            ,   
        " (c) Sangam poems have no reference to warrior ethic. "                  , 
        " (d) Sangam literature refers to magical forces as irrational. "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": "Consider the following pairs: King-  Dynasty \n1. Nannuka - Chandela \n2. jayashakti - Paramara \n3. Nagabhata II gurjara-Prathihara \n4. Bhoja - Rashtrakuta \nHow many pairs given above are correctly matched?      [UPSC 2022  ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) Only one pair "        , 
        " (b) Only two pairs "            ,   
        "(c) Only three pairs  "                  , 
        " (d) All four pairs "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": "Consider the following pairs: Site of Ashoka's major rock edicts Location in the State of \n1. Dhauli - Odisha \n2. Erragudi - Andhra Pradesh \n3. Jaugada - Madhya Pradesh \n4. Kalsi - Karnataka \nHow many pairs given above are correctly matched?     [UPSC 2022 ]",
      "choices": [
        "(a) Only one pair  "        , 
        " (b) Only two pairs "            ,   
        " (c) Only three pairs "                  , 
        " (d) All four pairs  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 0
    },{
      "question": " With reference to ancient India, consider the following statements: \n1. The concept of Stupa is Buddhist in origin. \n2. Stupa was generally a repository of relics. \n3. Stupa was a votive and commemorative structure in Buddhist tradition. \nHow many of the statements given above are correct?     [UPSC 2023 ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) Only one "        , 
        " (b) Only two "            ,   
        "(c) All three  "                  , 
        " (d) None "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": " Which one of the following explains the practice of 'Vattakirutal' as mentioned in Sangam poems?    [UPSC 2023 ]",
      "choices": [
        "(a) Kings employing women bodyguards "        , 
        " (b) Learned persons assembling in royal courts to discuss religious and philosophical matters "            ,   
        " (c) Young girls keeping watch over agricultural fields and driving away birds and animals "                  , 
        " (d) A king defeated in a battle committing ritual suicide by starving himself to death  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 3
    },{
      "question": "Consider the following dynasties: \n1. Hoysala \n2. Gahadavala \n3. Kakatiya \n4. Yadava \nHow many of the above dynasties established their kingdoms in early eighth century AD?  [UPSC 2023  ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) Only one "        , 
        "   (b) Only two"            ,   
        " (c) Only three "                  , 
        "   (d) None  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 3
    },{
      "question": "With reference to ancient Indian History, consider the following pairs: Literary work Author \n1.Devichandragupta : Bilhana \n2. Hammira-Mahakavya : Nayachandra Suri \n3. Milinda-panha: Nagarjuna \n4.Nitivakyamrita : Somadeva Suri \nHow many of the above pairs are correctly matched?    [UPSC 2023 ]",
      "choices": [
        " (a) Only one "        , 
        "(b) Only two  "            ,   
        "  (c) Only three  "                  , 
        " (d) All four "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": "'Souls are not only the property of animal and plant life, but also of rocks, running water and many other natural objects not looked on as living by other religious sects.' The above statement reflects one of the core beliefs of which one of the following religious sects of ancient India?     [UPSC 2023  ]",
      "choices": [
        "(a) Buddhism   "        , 
        " (b) Jainism "            ,   
        "(c) Shaivism  "                  , 
        "(d) Vaishnavism  "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    },{
      "question": " Consider the following pairs: Site Well known for \n1.Besnagar : Shaivite cave shrine \n2.Bhaja : Buddhist cave shrine \n3.Sittanavasal : Jain cave shrine \nHow many of the above pairs are correctly matched?    [UPSC  2023 ]",
      "choices": [
        "(a) Only one  "        , 
        " (b) Only two  "            ,   
        "  (c) All three"                  , 
        " (d) None "         
               
        ],
      "number": 99,
      "correct": 1
    }
  ]
}
